<?xml-model href="tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="DaughteroftheSamurai" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main"> A Daughter of the Samurai </title>
            </titleStmt>

            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
            </publicationStmt>

            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"/>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title level="a">A Daughter of the Samurai</title>
                    <editor/>
                    <author ref="#Etsu">Etsu Inagaki Sugimoto</author>
                    <date when="1925">1925</date>
                    <publisher>Doubleday, Page &amp; Company</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>New York City</pubPlace>
                    <orgName> </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="20210405">
                <name>Bryan Christman</name> Encoded A Daughter of the Samurai</change>

            <change when="20210302">
                <name>Amanda Gailey</name> Creation of template</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>



    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head type="number">CHAPTER XIV</head>
                <head type="title">LESSONS</head>
                <p>OUR time in school was supposed to be equally divided between Japanese and
                    English, but since I had been already carefully drilled in Japanese studies, I
                    was able to put my best efforts on English. My knowledge of that language was
                    very limited. I could read and write a little, but my spoken English was
                    scarcely understandable. I had, however, read a number of translations of
                    English books and&#8212;valuable than all else&#8212;I possessed a supply of
                    scattered knowledge obtained from a little set of books that my father had
                    brought me from the <placeName ref="#Tokyo">capital</placeName> when I was only
                    a child. They were translations, compiled from various sources and published by
                    one of the progressive book houses of <placeName ref="#Tokyo"
                    >Tokyo</placeName>.</p>
                <p>I do not know whose idea it was to translate and publish those ten little paper
                    volumes, but whoever it was holds my lasting gratitude. They brought the first
                    shafts of light that opened to my eager mind the wonders of the Western world,
                    and from them I was led to countless other friends and companions who, in the
                    years since, have brought to me such a wealth of knowledge and happiness that I
                    cannot think what life would have been without them. How well I remember the day
                    they came! Father had gone to <placeName ref="#Tokyo">Tokyo</placeName> on one
                    of his <q>“window toward growing days”</q> trips.</p>
                <p>That was always an important event in our lives, for he brought back with him,
                    not only wonderful stories of his journey, but also gifts of strange and
                    beautiful things. Mother had said that he would be home at the close of the day,
                    and I spent the afternoon sitting on the porch step watching the
                    slow-lengthening shadows of the garden trees. I had placed my high wooden clogs
                    on a stepping-stone just at the edge of the longest shadow, and as the sun crept
                    farther I moved them from stone to stone, following the sunshine. I think I must
                    have had a vague feeling that I could thus hasten the slanting shadow into the
                    long straight line which would mean sunset.</p>
                <p>At last&#8212;at last&#8212;and before the shadow had quite straightened, I
                    hurriedly snatched up the clogs and clattered across the stones, for I had heard
                    the <term xml:lang="ja" ref="#def1">jinrikisha</term> man's cry of <term
                        xml:lang="ja" ref="#def2"><q>“<hi rend="italics">Okaeri!</hi>”</q></term>
                    just outside the gate. I could scarcely bear my joy, and I have a bit of guilt
                    in my heart yet when I recall how crookedly I pushed those clogs into the neat
                    box of shelves in the <q>“shoe-off”</q> alcove of the vestibule.</p>
                <p>The next moment the men, perspiring and laughing, came trotting up to the door
                    where we, servants and all, were gathered, our heads bowed to the floor, all in
                    a quiver of excitement and delight, but of course everybody gravely saying the
                    proper words of greeting. Then, my duty done, I was caught up in my father's
                    arms and we went to Honourable Grandmother, who was the only one of the
                    household who might wait in her room for the coming of the master of the
                    house.</p>
                <p>That day was one of the <q>“memory stones”</q> of my life, for among all the
                    wonderful and beautiful things which were taken from the willow-wood boxes
                    straddled over the shoulders of the servants was the set of books for me. I can
                    see them now. Ten small volumes of tough Japanese paper, tied together with silk
                    cord and marked, <title ref="#WesternSeas"><q>“Tales of the Western
                        Seas.”</q></title> They held extracts from <title ref="#WorldHistory"
                            ><q>“Peter Parley's World History,”</q></title>
                    <title ref="#NationalReader"><q>“National Reader,”</q></title>
                    <title ref="#WilsonsReaders"><q>“Wilson's Readers,”</q></title> and many short
                    poems and tales from classic authors in English literature.</p>
                <p>The charm of delight that rare things give came to me during days and
                    weeks&#8212;even months and years&#8212;from those books. I can recite whole
                    pages of them now. There was a most interesting story of <persName
                        ref="#Colombus">Christopher Columbus.</persName> It was not translated
                    literally, but adapted so that the Japanese mind would readily grasp the thought
                    without being buried in a puzzling mass of strange customs. All facts of the
                    wonderful discovery were stated truthfully, but <persName ref="#Colombus"
                        >Columbus</persName> was pictured as a fisher lad, and somewhere in the
                    story there figured a lacquer bowl and a pair of chopsticks.</p>
                <p>These books had been my inspiration during all my years of childhood, and when,
                    in my study of English at school, my clumsy mind began to grasp the fact that,
                    hidden beneath the puzzling words were continuations of stories I knew, and of
                    ideas similar to those I had found in the old familiar books that I had loved so
                    well, my delight was unbounded. Then I began to read eagerly. I would bend over
                    my desk, hurrying, guessing, skipping whole lines, stumbling along&#8212;my
                    dictionary wide open beside me, but I not having time to look&#8212;and yet, in
                    some marvellous way, catching ideas. And I never wearied. The fascination was
                    like that of a moon-gazing party, where, while we watched from the hillside
                    platform, a floating cloud would sail across the glorious disk, and
                    we&#8212;silent, trembling with excitement&#8212;would wait for the glory of the
                    coming moment. In the same way, a half-hidden thought&#8212;elusive,
                    tantalizing&#8212;would fill me with a breathless hope that the next moment
                    light would come. Another thing about English books was that, as I read, I was
                    constantly discovering shadowy replies to the unanswered questions of my
                    childhood. Oh, English books were a source of deepest joy!</p>
                <p>"I am afraid that I should not have been so persistent, or so successful in my
                    English studies, could I have readily obtained translations of the books I was
                    so eager to read. <placeName ref="#Tokyo">Tokyo</placeName> bookshops, at that
                    time, were beginning to be flooded with translations of English, French, German,
                    and Russian books; and these generally, if not scientific treatises, were
                    classics translated, as a rule, by our best scholars; but they were expensive to
                    purchase and difficult for me to obtain in any other way. To read, even
                    stumblingly, in the original, the books in the school library was my only
                    resource, and it became one of my greatest pleasures.</p>
                <p>Excepting English, of all my studies history was the favourite; and I liked and
                    understood best the historical books of the <title ref="#OldTestament">Old
                        Testament.</title> The figurative language was something like Japanese; the
                    old heroes had the same virtues and the same weaknesses of our ancient <term
                        xml:lang="ja" ref="#def3">samurai</term>; the patriarchal form of government
                    was like ours, and the family system based upon it pictured so plainly our own
                    homes that the meaning of many questioned passages was far less puzzling to me
                    than were the explanations of the foreign teachers.</p>
                <p>In my study of English literature, it seems odd that, of all the treasures that I
                    gathered, the one which has been most lasting as a vivid picture, is that of
                        <persName ref="#Tennyson">Tennyson</persName>'s <title ref="#Dora"
                        >“Dora.”</title> Probably this was because of its having been used by a
                        <persName ref="#Kencho">famous Japanese writer</persName> as the foundation
                    of a novel called <term xml:lang="ja" xml:id="Lily"><title ref="#Tanima"
                                ><q>“Tanima no Himeyuri.”</q></title></term>&#8212;<gloss
                        target="#Lily">Lily of the Valley.</gloss> The story of Dora, being a tale
                    of the first-born of an aristocratic family disinherited because he loved a
                    rustic lass of humble class; and the subsequent tragedy resulting from the
                    difference in training of different social circles, was a tale familiar and
                    understandable to us. It was skilfully handled, the author, with wonderful word
                    pictures, adapting Western life and thought to Japanese conditions.</p>
                <p><title ref="#Tanima"><q>“The Lily of the Valley”</q></title> appeared at just the
                    time when the young mind of Japan, both high and humble, was beginning to seek
                    emancipation from the stoic philosophy, which for centuries had been the core of
                    our well-bred training, and it touched the heart of the public. The book rushed
                    with a storm of popularity all through the land and was read by all classes;
                    and&#8212;which was unusual&#8212;by both men and women. It is said that
                        <persName ref="#Shoken">Her Imperial Majesty</persName> became so interested
                    in reading it that she sat up all one night while her court ladies, sitting
                    silent in the next room, wearily waited.</p>
                <p>I think it was my third year in school that a wave of excitement over love
                    stories struck <placeName ref="#Tokyo">Tokyo</placeName>. All the schoolgirls
                    were wildly interested. When translations were to be had we passed them from
                    hand to hand through the school; but mostly we had to struggle along in English,
                    picking out love scenes from the novels and poems in our school library. <title
                        ref="#EnochArden">Enoch Arden</title> was our hero. We were familiar with
                    loyalty and sacrifice on the part of a wife, and understood perfectly why Annie
                    should have so long withstood the advances of Philip, but the unselfishness of
                    the faithful Enoch was so rare as to be much appreciated.</p>
                <p>The hearts of Japanese girls are no different from those of girls of other
                    countries, but for centuries, especially in <term xml:lang="ja" ref="#def3"
                        >samurai</term> homes, we had been strictly trained to regard duty, not
                    feeling, as the standard of relations between man and woman. Thus our unguided
                    reading sometimes gave us warped ideas on this unknown subject. The impression I
                    received was that love as pictured in Western books was interesting and
                    pleasant, sometimes beautiful in sacrifice like that of Enoch Arden; but not to
                    be compared in strength, nobility, or loftiness of spirit to the affection of
                    parent for child, or the loyalty between lord and vassal.</p>
                <p>Had my opinion been allowed to remain wordless, it probably would never have
                    caused me annoyance, but it was destined to see the light. We had a very
                    interesting literature society which held an occasional special meeting, to
                    which we invited the teachers as guests. With an anxious pride to have a fine
                    entertainment, we frequently planned our programme first and afterward selected
                    the girls for the various tasks. The result was that sometimes the subject
                    chosen was beyond the capacity of the girl to handle. At one time this rule
                    brought disaster to me, for we never shirked any duty to which we were
                    assigned.</p>
                <p>On this occasion I was asked to prepare a three-page essay in English, having one
                    of the cardinal virtues for a subject. I puzzled over which to select of Faith,
                    Hope, Charity, Love, Prudence, and Patience; but recalling that our Bible
                    teacher frequently quoted <q>“God is Love,”</q> I felt that there I had a
                    foundation, and so chose as my topic, <q>“Love.”</q> I began with the love of
                    the Divine Father, then, under the influence of my late reading, I drifted
                    along, rather vaguely, I fear, on the effect of love on the lives of celebrated
                    characters in history and poetry. But I did not know how to handle so awkward a
                    subject, and reached my limit in both knowledge and vocabulary before the three
                    pages were filled. Faithfulness to duty, however, still held firm, and I wrote
                    on, finally concluding with these words: <q>“Love is like a powerful medicine.
                        When properly used it will prove a pleasant tonic, and sometimes may even
                        preserve life; but when misused, it can ruin nations, as seen in the lives
                        of <persName ref="#Cleopatra">Cleopatra</persName> and the beloved <persName
                            ref="#ChineseEmpress">Empress of the Emperor Genso of Great
                            China</persName>.”</q></p>
                <p>At the close of my reading one teacher remarked, <q>“This is almost
                        desecration.”</q></p>
                <p>It was years before I understood what the criticism meant.</p>
                <p>For a while my great interest in English reading filled all my hours of leisure,
                    but there came a time when my heart longed for the dear old stories of Japan,
                    and I wrote to my mother asking her to send me some books from home. Among
                    others she selected a popular classic called <title ref="#Hakkenden"
                        xml:lang="ja"><q>“Hakkenden,”</q></title> which I especially loved. It is
                    the longest novel ever written in the Japanese language, and our copy,
                    Japanese-bound and elaborately illustrated, consisted of 180 volumes. With great
                    effort Mother succeeded in obtaining a foreign-bound copy in two thick volumes.
                    I welcomed these books with joy, and was amazed when one of the teachers, seeing
                    them in my bookcase, took them away, saying they were not proper books for me to
                    read.</p>
                <p>To me, <title ref="#Hakkenden" xml:lang="ja">
                        <q>“Hakkenden,”</q></title> with its wonderful symbolism, was one of the
                    most inspiring books I had ever read. It was written in the 18th Century by
                        <persName ref="#Bakin">Bakin</persName>, our great philosopher-novelist, and
                    so musical is the literature, and so lofty the ideals, that frequently it has
                    been compared, by Japanese of learning, to <persName ref="#Milton"
                        >Milton</persName>’s <title ref="#ParadiseLost"><q>“Paradise
                        Lost”</q></title> and the <title ref="#DivineComedy"><q>“Divine
                        Comedy”</q></title> of <persName ref="#Dante">Dante</persName>. The
                        <persName ref="#Bakin">author</persName> was a strong believer in the
                    unusual theory of spiritual transmigration, and his story is based on that
                    belief.</p>
                <p>The tale is of the <term xml:lang="ja" ref="#def4">daimio</term> Satomi, who,
                    with his almost starving retainers, was holding his castle against a besieging
                    army. Knowing that the strength of the enemy lay alone in their able general, he
                    desperately offered everything he possessed, even to his precious daughter, to
                    any one brave enough to destroy his enemy. Satomi's faithful dog, a handsome
                    wolf-hound named Yatsubusa, bounded away, and the next morning appeared before
                    his master, carrying by its long hair the head of Satomi's foe. With their
                    leader gone the enemy was thrown into confusion, and Satomi's warriors, with a
                    mighty rush, put them to flight. Thus was the province restored to peace and
                    prosperity. Then, so bitterly did Satomi regret his promise that he was enraged
                    at the very sight of the faithful animal to whom he owed his good fortune. But
                    his beautiful daughter, the Princess Fuse, pitied the wronged animal.</p>
                <p><q>“The word of a <term xml:lang="ja" ref="#def3">samurai</term>, once uttered,
                        cannot be recalled,”</q> she said. <q>“It is my duty to uphold the honour of
                        my father's word.”</q></p>
                <p>So the filial daughter went with Yatsubusa to a mountain cave where she spent her
                    time in praying to the gods that a soul might be given to the brave animal; and
                    with every murmured prayer the noble nature of the dumb Yatsubusa drew nearer to
                    the border line of human intelligence.</p>
                <p>One day there came to the mountain a loyal retainer of Satomi. He saw, just
                    within the cave, the Princess Fuse sitting before the shrine holding an open
                    book. Before her, like a faithful vassal, Yatsubusa listened with bowed head to
                    the holy reading. Believing he was doing a noble deed, the retainer lifted his
                    gun and fired. The bullet, swift and strong, was guided by fate. It passed
                    directly through the body of Yatsubusa and on, piercing the heart of the
                    Princess Fuse.</p>
                <p>At that instant the freed spirit of the Princess, as eight shining stars in a
                    floating mist, rose from her body and floated softly through the sky to the
                    eight corners of the world. Each star was a virtue: Loyalty, Sincerity, Filial
                    Piety, Friendship, Charity, Righteousness, Courtesy, and Wisdom.</p>
                <p>Fate guided each star to a human home, and in course of time, into each of these
                    homes a son was born. As they blossomed into manhood, Fate brought the youths
                    together, and the reunited eight virtues become heroic vassals, through whom
                    came glory to the name of Satomi. So the spirit of the filial daughter brought
                    honour to her father's name.</p>
                <p>I could not understand why this miracle-story, filled with lofty symbolism, could
                    be more objectionable than the many fables and fairy tales of personified
                    animals that I had read in English literature. But, after much pondering, I
                    concluded that thoughts, like the language, on one side of the world are
                    straightforward and literal; and on the other, vague, mystical, and
                    visionary.</p>
                <p>At the end of my school life my beloved books were returned to me. I have them
                    now&#8212;battered, loose-leafed, and worn&#8212;and I still love them.</p>
                <p>As time passed on, I learned to like almost everything about my school&#8212;even
                    many of the things which at first I had found most trying; but there was one
                    thing which from the very first I had enjoyed with my whole heart. The school
                    building was surrounded by large grounds with tall trees. A small lawn near the
                    principal doorway was well cared for, but beyond was an extensive stretch of
                    weedy grass and untrained shrubbery. There were no stone lanterns, no pond with
                    darting gold-fish, and no curving bridge; just big trees with unbound branches,
                    uncut grass, and&#8212;freedom to grow.</p>
                <p>At my home there was one part of the garden that was supposed to be wild. The
                    trees were twisted like wind-blown mountain pines; the stepping-stones marked an
                    irregular path across ground covered with pine needles; the fence was of growing
                    cedar peeping between uneven rods of split bamboo, and the gate was of brushwood
                    tied with rough twine. But someone was always busy trimming the pines or cutting
                    the hedge, and every morning Jiya wiped off the stepping-stones and, after
                    sweeping beneath the pine trees, carefully scattered fresh pine needles gathered
                    from the forest. There the wildness was only constant repression, but here at
                    the school everything was filled with the uplifting freshness of unrestrained
                    freedom. This I enjoyed with a happiness so great that the very fact that such
                    happiness could exist in the human heart was a surprise to me.</p>
                <p>One section of this wild ground the teachers divided into small gardens, giving
                    one to each of the girls and providing any kind of flower seeds we wanted. This
                    was a new delight. I already loved the free growth of the trees, and the grass
                    on which I could walk even in my shoes; but this <q>“plant-what-you-please”</q>
                    garden gave me a wholly new feeling of personal right. I, with no violation of
                    tradition, no stain on the family name, no shock to parent, teacher, or
                    townspeople, no harm to anything in the world, was free to act. So instead of
                    having a low bamboo fence around my garden, as most of the girls had, I went to
                    the kitchen and coaxed the cook to give me some dried branches used for
                    kindling. Then I made a rustic hedge, and, in my garden, instead of flowers, I
                    planted&#8212;potatoes.</p>
                <p>No one knows the sense of reckless freedom which this absurd act gave
                    me&#8212;nor the consequences to which it led. It had unloosed my soul, and I
                    stood listening, while from a strange tangle of unconventional smiles and
                    informal acts, of outspoken words and unhidden thoughts, of growing trees and
                    untouched grass, the spirit of freedom came knocking at my door.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head type="number">CHAPTER XV </head>
                <head type="title"> HOW I BECAME A CHRISTIAN</head>
                <p>IN MY <placeName ref="#Nagaoka">Nagaoka</placeName> home, notwithstanding the
                    love and care that surrounded me, my mind was always filled with unanswered
                    questions. My education as a priestess had developed my mind, but it had grown
                    in cramped silence; for, liberal as was my father in his views regarding my
                    training, I was influenced by the home atmosphere of conservatism, and rarely
                    spoke, even to him, of my inmost thoughts.</p>
                <p>But occasionally this reserve was broken. Once, just after I had made many bows
                    of farewell to the departing guests of the three-hundredth death celebration of
                    an ancestor, I asked:</p>
                <p>
                    <q>“Honourable Father, who is the first, the away-back, the very beginning of
                        our ancestors?”</q>
                </p>
                <p><q>“Little daughter,”</q> Father gravely answered, <q>“that is a presumptuous
                        question for a well-bred girl to ask; but I will be honest and tell you that
                        I do not know. Our great <persName ref="#Confucius">Confucius</persName>
                        replied to his disciple concerning that very question, <q>'We know not
                            life.’</q>”</q></p>
                <p>I was very young, but I well understood that I must in the future be more demure
                    and womanly in my inquiries, and not ask questions with the freedom of a
                    boy.</p>
                <p>The influence of my school life in <placeName ref="#Tokyo">Tokyo</placeName> had
                    been subtle. Unconsciously I had expanded, until gradually I became convinced
                    that asking questions was only a part of normal development. Then, for the first
                    time in my life, I attempted to put into words some of the secret thoughts of my
                    heart. This was gently encouraged by my tactful teachers; and, as time passed
                    on, I realized more and more that they were wonderfully wise for women, and my
                    confidence in them grew. Not only this, but their effortless influence to
                    inspire happiness changed my entire outlook on life. My childhood had been
                    happy, but it had never known one throb of what may be called joyousness. I used
                    to gaze at the full moon sailing in the deep sky, with all the poetic ecstasy of
                    the Japanese heart, but always, like a shadow, came the thought, <q>“It will
                        grow less from to-night.”</q> Our flower viewings were a delight to me, but
                    invariably, as I travelled homeward, I sighed to myself: <q>“The lovely blossoms
                        will fall before the winds of tomorrow.”</q> So it was with everything. In
                    the midst of gladness I unconsciously sent out a heart search for a thread of
                    sadness. I ascribe this morbid tendency to the Buddhist teaching of my
                    childhood; for there is a strain of hopeless sadness in all
                        <note>Buddhist</note> thought.</p>
                <p>But my life at school blew into my heart a breath of healthful cheerfulness. As
                    the restraint which had held me like a vise began to relax, so also there melted
                    within me the tendency to melancholy. It could not be otherwise; for the
                    teachers, whether working, playing, laughing, or even reproving, were a
                    continual surprise. In my home, surprises had been infrequent. People bowed,
                    walked, talked, and smiled exactly as they had bowed, walked, talked, and smiled
                    yesterday, and the day before, and in all past time. But these astonishing
                    teachers were never the same. They changed so unexpectedly in voice and manner
                    with each person to whom they spoke, that their very changeableness was a
                    refreshing attraction. They reminded me of cherry blossoms.</p>
                <p>Japanese people love flowers for what they mean. I was taught from babyhood that
                    the plum, bravely pushing its blossoms through the snows of early spring, is our
                    bridal flower because it is an emblem of duty through hardship. The cherry is
                    beautiful and it never fades, for the lightest breeze scatters the still fresh
                    and fragrant petals into another beauty of tinted, floating clouds; which again
                    changes to a carpet of delicate white-and-pink shells&#8212;like my teachers,
                    always changing and always beautiful.</p>
                <p>Although I now know that my first impressions of American womanhood were
                    exaggerated, I have never regretted this idealization; for through it I came to
                    realize the tragic truth that the Japanese woman&#8212;like the plum blossom,
                    modest, gentle, and bearing unjust hardship without complaint&#8212;is often
                    little else than a useless sacrifice; while the American
                    woman&#8212;self-respecting, untrammelled, changing with quick adaptability to
                    new conditions&#8212;carries inspiration to every heart, because her life, like
                    the blossom of the cherry, blooms in freedom and naturalness.</p>
                <p>This realization was of slow growth, and it brought with it much silent
                    questioning.</p>
                <p>From childhood I had known, as did all Japanese people, that woman is greatly
                    inferior to man. This I never questioned. It was fate. But as I grew older I so
                    constantly saw that fate brings inconvenience and humiliation to blameless
                    people that I fell into a habit of puzzling, in a crude, childish way, over this
                    great unkind Power. At last a day came when my heart broke into open
                    rebellion.</p>
                <p>Ever since the hard days before the Restoration<ref target="#note1">*</ref>, my
                    mother had been subject to occasional attacks of asthma, which we all were
                    sincere in believing was due to some unknown wrong committed by her in a
                    previous existence. Once when, after a breathless struggle, I heard her gasp,
                        <q>“It is fate and must be borne,”</q> I ran to Ishi and asked indignantly
                    why fate made my mother suffer.</p>
                <p><q>“It cannot be helped,”</q> she replied, with pitying tears in her eyes. <q>“It
                        is because of the unworthiness of woman. But you must be calm, <persName
                            ref="#Etsu">Etsu-bo Sama</persName>. The Honourable Mistress does not
                        complain. She is proud to bear silently.”</q></p>
                <p>I was too young to understand, but, with my heart pounding in hot rebellion
                    against the powerful, mysterious injustice, I pulled myself into Ishi's lap and,
                    convulsively clinging to her, begged her to tell me a story&#8212;quick&#8212;of
                    clashing swords, and flying arrows, and heroes who fought and won.</p>
                <p>Japanese children were not taught that rebellious thoughts, if unexpressed, are a
                    wrong to the gods, so the resentment in my heart grew. But as it grew there
                    slowly drifted into, and curiously blended with it, a blind wonder why my mother
                    and Ishi, when hardship came for which they were not to blame, should submit to
                    it, not only dutifully and patiently&#8212;that, of course, it was their place,
                    as women, to do&#8212;but with pride. Something within me cried out that,
                    however dutiful they might be in act, their <hi rend="italics">hearts</hi> ought
                    to rebel; yet I had known both unnecessarily to accept a humiliating blame that
                    they knew was not theirs! That those two noble women should encourage
                    self-humiliation I resented more bitterly than I did the hard decrees of
                    fate.</p>
                <p>Of course, this thought was not clear in my mind at that time. Then and for years
                    after, my idea of fate&#8212; for in fate I firmly believed&#8212;was of a
                    vague, floating, stupendous power, for which I felt only resentful wonder.</p>
                <p> Another puzzle came one midsummer airing day. It seems odd that it should have
                    happened then, for airing days were the most care-free, happy time of the year
                    for me. Then the godowns were emptied and long ropes stretched in the sunshine,
                    on which were hung torn banners bearing our crest, old field-curtains used in
                    the camps of our ancestors, ancient regalia of house officers, and many
                    odd-shaped garments belonging to what Ishi's fairy tales called <q>“the olden,
                        olden time.”</q> Beneath the low eaves were piles of clumsy horse armour
                    bound with faded ropes of twisted silk; and old war weapons&#8212;spears,
                    battle-axes, bows, and sheaves of arrows&#8212;stood in out-of-the-way corners
                    of the garden. All available space was utilized; even the bridge-posts and the
                    stone lanterns were decorated with chain-silk armour and lacquer helmets with
                    fearful masks.</p>
                <p>The confusion was delightful. I loved it. And Father would walk around with me,
                    showing me things and explaining their use, until, all perspiring and with eyes
                    dazzled by the sun, we would go indoors and stumble through the cluttered-up
                    halls to Honourable Grandmother's room. That seemed to be the only place in the
                    house in order. Everywhere else were busy servants brushing, folding, or
                    carrying, and at the same time all chattering gayly; for airing days, although
                    bringing hard work, were a happy diversion in our rather monotonous household
                    and always cordially welcomed by the servants.</p>
                <p>When Father and I reached Honourable Grandmother's room we found ourselves
                    suddenly shut away from all the turmoil into a place cool and quiet. I can see
                    Father now, as, with a sigh of satisfaction, he closed the door behind him and,
                    pushing aside the proffered cushion, bowed his thanks to Honourable Grandmother
                    and seated himself on the cool straw mat beside the open doors overlooking the
                    shady <q>“wild garden.”</q> There he would sit, fanning himself and talking with
                    Honourable Grandmother of old times.</p>
                <p>Once, just after the noon meal of hot whale soup and eggplant, which was always
                    served on airing days, Father went directly to his room. I was hurrying after
                    him when I saw Jiya and another manservant in their stiff crestdresses crossing
                    the garden from the godown. They were carrying, reverentially, a whitewood chest
                    shaped like a temple box for sacred books. On the front, very large, was our
                    crest, and around it was tied a straw rope with dangling Shinto papers. Many
                    times I had seen that chest in the godown, standing alone on a whitewood
                    platform. It held family heirlooms, some of them centuries old. The men were on
                    their way to a certain room which Mother had prepared, where the chest would be
                    opened in silence, and the sacred articles carefully examined by men in
                    ceremonial garments.</p>
                <p> I sat down listlessly on the edge of the porch, for I knew that Father, dressed
                    in his stately <term xml:lang="ja" ref="#def5">kamishimo</term> garments, would
                    soon go to the room where the heirloom chest had been taken, and I should see
                    him no more that afternoon. On airing days I generally followed him wherever he
                    went, but across the threshold of that room I should not be allowed to step. I
                    did not wonder why. It had always been so.</p>
                <p>But as I sat alone on the porch I began to think, and after a while I hunted up
                    Ishi.</p>
                <p><q>“Ishi,”</q> I said, <q>“I go everywhere else with Father. Why cannot I be with
                        him in the room where they are airing the sacred things?”</q></p>
                <p><q>“<persName ref="#Etsu">Etsu-bo Sama</persName>,”</q> she replied in the most
                    matter-of-fact tone, as she shook out the long fringe of an old-fashioned
                    incense ball, <q>“it is because you were born a daughter to your father instead
                        of a son.”</q></p>
                <p>I felt that her words were a personal reproach, and with the age-old, patient
                    submission of the Japanese woman, I walked slowly toward Honourable
                    Grandmother's room. It was comforting to turn my mind toward my stately, noble
                    grandmother, to whom the entire household, even Father, looked up with
                    reverence. Then, suddenly, like a breath of cold wind, came the thought that
                    even my saintly grandmother would not dare touch the sacred things that were
                    used to honour the Shinto gods. She always attended to the Buddhist shrine, but
                    it was Father's duty to care for the white Shinto shrine. During his absence,
                    Jiya or another manservant took his place, for no woman was worthy to handle
                    such holy things. And yet the great god of Shinto was a woman&#8212;the Sun
                        goddess!<ref target="#note2">*</ref></p>
                <p>That night I was bold enough to ask my father if his honourable mother was an
                    unworthy woman like all others.</p>
                <p><q>“What do you think, little Daughter?”</q> he asked, after a moment's
                    hesitation.</p>
                <p><q>“It cannot be,”</q> I replied. <q>“You honour her too greatly for it to be
                        true.”</q></p>
                <p>He smiled and tenderly touched my head with his hand.</p>
                <p><q>“Continue to believe so, little Daughter,”</q> he said gently. <q>“And yet do
                        not forget the stern teachings of your childhood. They form the current of a
                        crystal stream that, as it flows through the ages, keeps Japanese women
                        worthy&#8212;like your grandmother.”</q></p>
                <p>It was not until long, long afterward, when the knowledge of later years had
                    broadened my mind, that I comprehended his hidden meaning that a woman may
                    quietly harbour independent thought if she does not allow it to destroy her
                    gentle womanhood. The night that this thought came to me I wrote in my diary:
                        <q>“Useless sacrifice leads to&#8212;only a sigh. Self-respect leads
                        to&#8212;freedom and hope.”</q></p>
                <p>Beyond the wall on one side of our school was a rough path leading past several
                    small villages, with ricefields and patches of clover scattered between. One
                    day, when a teacher was taking a group of us girls for a walk, we came upon a
                    dry ricefield dotted with wild flowers. We were gathering them with merry
                    chattering and laughter when two village farmers passed by, walking slowly and
                    watching us curiously.</p>
                <p><q>“What is the world coming to,”</q> said one, <q>“when workable-age young
                        misses waste time wandering about through bushes and wild grass?”</q></p>
                <p><q>“They are grasshoppers trying to climb the mountain,”</q> the other replied,
                        <q>“but the sun will scorch them with scorn. There can be only pity for the
                        young man who takes one of those for his bride.”</q></p>
                <p>The men were rough and ignorant, but they were men: and though we all laughed,
                    not one of the girls was far enough from the shackles of her mother's day not to
                    feel a shadow of discomfort as we walked homeward.</p>
                <p>The teacher paused as we came to the moss-covered stone wall of an old shrine and
                    pointed to a near-by cherry tree, young and thrifty, growing out of the hollow
                    of another tree whose fallen trunk was so old and twisted that it looked like a
                    rough-scaled dragon. Beside it was one of the wooden standards so often seen in
                    an artistic or noted spot. On the tablet was inscribed the poem:</p>
                <quote> “The blossoms of to-day draw strength from the roots of a thousand years
                    ago.” </quote>
                <p><q>“This tree is like you girls,”</q> said the teacher, with a smile. <q>“Japan’s
                        beautiful old civilization has given its strength to you young women of
                        to-day. Now it is your duty to grow bravely and give to new Japan, in
                        return, a greater strength and beauty than even the old possessed. Do not
                        forget!”</q></p>
                <p>We walked on homeward. Just as we reached our gate in the hedge wall one of the
                    girls, who had been rather quiet, turned to me.</p>
                <p><q>“Nevertheless,”</q> she said, defiantly, <q>“the grasshoppers are climbing the
                        mountain into the sunlight.”</q></p>
                <p>As I learned to value womanhood, I realized more and more that my love of freedom
                    and my belief in my right to grow toward it meant more than freedom to act, to
                    talk, to think. Freedom also claimed a spiritual right to grow.</p>
                <p>I do not know exactly how I became a Christian. It was not a sudden thing. It
                    seems to have been a natural spiritual development&#8212;so natural that only a
                    few puzzles stand out clearly as I look back along the path. As I read, and
                    thought, and felt, my soul reached out into the unknown; and gradually, easily,
                    almost unconsciously, I drifted out of a faith of philosophy, mysticism, and
                    resignation into one of high ideals, freedom, cheerfulness, and hope.</p>
                <p>Of the wonder and glory of what I consider the greatest faith of the world I do
                    not speak. Of that many know. And the selfish gain to me is beyond all words of
                    all languages.</p>
                <p>When I was sent to the mission school the fact that the teachers were of another
                    religion was not considered at all. They were thought of only as teachers of the
                    language and manners of America; so when I wrote to Mother, asking her consent
                    to my becoming a Christian, I know she was greatly surprised. But she was a wise
                    woman. She replied, <q>“My daughter, this is an important thing. I think it will
                        be best for you to wait until vacation. Then we will talk of it.”</q></p>
                <p>So I postponed being baptized, and when vacation came, I went to <placeName
                        ref="#Nagaoka">Nagaoka</placeName>. The people there knew little of
                    Christianity.<ref target="#note3">*</ref> The only impression most of them had
                    was that it was a curious belief lacking in ceremony, whose converts were
                    required to trample upon sacred things<ref target="#note4">*</ref> There
                    existed, especially among the old, a strong distaste against <term xml:lang="ja"
                        xml:id="Jakyo">Jakyo</term>, <gloss target="#Jakyo">the evil sect</gloss>,
                    but it held no vital, forceful bitterness. The people of <placeName
                        ref="#Nagaoka">Nagaoka</placeName> looked upon the stories of Japan's
                    Christian martyrs<ref target="#note5">*</ref> as a distant and pitiful thing;
                    but they had none of the shuddering horror felt in some communities of southern
                    Japan, whose memories of the tragedies of four centuries ago had reason to
                    live.</p>
                <p>My mother, who had learned from Father to be tolerant of the opinions of others,
                    had no prejudice against the new religion; but she believed that the great duty
                    in life for sons and daughters consisted in a rigid observance of the ritual for
                    ancestor-worship and the ceremonies in memory of the dead. When I first reached
                    home her heart was heavy with dread, but when she learned that my new faith did
                    not require disrespect to ancestors, her relief and gratitude were pathetic, and
                    she readily gave her consent.</p>
                <p>But Honourable Grandmother! My proud, loyal grandmother! It was impossible for
                    her to understand, and I think my becoming a heretic was to her a lifelong
                    sorrow. Her grief was my heaviest cross.</p>
                <p>It was hard, too, to visit my relatives and friends. They looked upon me as a
                    curiosity, and my mother was in a continual state of explanation and apology.
                    One old aunt closed the doors of her shrine and pasted white paper over them
                    that the ancestors might be spared the knowledge of my <q>“peculiarity.”</q></p>
                <p>Another aunt, who invited me out to dinner, served no fish, feeling that, since I
                    was so puzzlingly removed from ordinary life, I could not be feasted in the
                    usual way. After discarding one plan after another, she finally concluded it
                    would be both harmless and respectful for her to treat me as a priest.</p>
                <p>All these things among the friends that I had known from babyhood hurt me. I
                    could bravely have borne persecution, but to be set apart as something strange
                    almost broke my heart. How I longed for my father! He would have understood, but
                    I was alone in the midst of kindly ignorance. Everybody loved me, but they all
                    looked at me in helpless pity.</p>
                <p>At first I was unhappy, but my three months at home changed everything, both for
                    my friends and for myself. When I returned to school I carried with me all the
                    respect and love of the home friends that had always been mine, and
                    which&#8212;thank God&#8212;I have kept until now.</p>
                <p>I think I am a true Christian. At least my belief has given me untold comfort and
                    a perfect heart-satisfaction, but it has never separated me from my Buddhist
                    friends. They have respect for this strange belief of mine; for they feel that,
                    although I am loyal to the Christian God, I still keep the utmost reverence for
                    my fathers and respect for the faith that was the highest and holiest thing they
                    knew.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
    <standOff>
        <listAnnotation type="footnotes">
            <note xml:id="note1">*The Meiji Restoration was an 1868 political revolution that
                reconsolidated power under the Emperor Meiji, ended the feudal rule of the <ref
                    target="#def4"><hi rend="italics">daimyos</hi></ref> and accelerated Japan's
                industrialization and modernization.</note>
            <note xml:id="note2">*The Sun goddess of Shinto is known by the name Amaterasu Omikami,
                which means "Great Divinity Illuminating Heaven." She is considered to be the ruler
                of heaven and the ancestress of the Japanese imperial family.</note>
            <note xml:id="note3">*Jesuit missionaries arrived in Japan during the 16th century and
                converted over a hundred thousand people to Christianity. After Toyotomi Hideyoshi
                became ruler of Japan, he became suspicious of Christianity as a foreign threat and
                had the religion repressed and its adherents persecuted. The next ruler, Tokugawa
                Ieyasu, issued an edict officially banning Christianity in 1614. Any remaining
                Christians were driven into hiding until religious freedom was re-established during
                the 19th century.</note>
            <note xml:id="note4">*The Japanese government would force suspected Christians to
                renounce the faith by stepping on images of Jesus and Mary called <hi rend="italics"
                    >fumie</hi></note>
            <note xml:id="note5">*Twenty-six Christians were executed by crucifixion in Nagasaki in
                1597 and became known as the Twenty-six Martyrs of Japan.</note>
        </listAnnotation>
        <listAnnotation type="JapaneseWords">
            <note xml:id="def1"><hi rend="italics">Jinrikisha</hi>: Japanese term for a two or three
                wheeled passenger cart pulled by a single man on foot, which was a popular form of
                transportation in Japan during the 19th Century; the word is a combination of <hi
                    rend="italics">jin</hi>, meaning "human," <hi rend="italics">riki</hi>, meaning
                "power," and <hi rend="italics">sha</hi>, meaning "vehicle," thus "human-powered
                vehicle"</note>
            <note xml:id="def2"><hi rend="italics">Okaeri</hi>: a shortened version of the Japanese
                expression "Okaerinasai" which means "welcome home"; literally, "you have come
                home"</note>
            <note xml:id="def3"><hi rend="italics">Samurai</hi>: the prestigious Japanese warrior
                class who served the <ref target="#def4">daimyo</ref> from the 12th century until
                the <ref target="#note1">Meiji Restoration</ref>; the word comes from the verb <hi
                    rend="italics">saburau</hi> which means "to serve" </note>
            <note xml:id="def4"><hi rend="italics">Daimio</hi>: Japanese feudal lords who owned and
                ruled over most of the land from the 10th century until the <ref target="#note1"
                    >Meiji Restoration</ref>; the word is a combination of <hi rend="italics"
                    >dai</hi>, which means "large," and <hi rend="italics">myo</hi>, a short form of
                    <hi rend="italics">myoden</hi>, which means "private land"</note>
            <note xml:id="def5"><hi rend="italics">Kamishimo</hi>: Traditional formal clothing worn
                by <ref target="#def3">samurai</ref></note>
        </listAnnotation>
        <listPlace>
            <place xml:id="Tokyo" type="city">
                <placeName>Tokyo, Japan</placeName>
                <note>Tokyo, literally "eastern capital," became the capital city of Japan during
                    the <ref target="note1">Meiji Restoration.</ref>
                </note>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Nagaoka" type="city">
                <placeName>Nagoaka, Japan</placeName>
                <note>Once a town in Echigo Province, now a city in Niigata Prefecture. The town was
                    destroyed during the battle of Hokuetsu during the <ref target="#note1">Meiji
                        Restoration</ref> and rebuilt afterwards.</note>
            </place>
        </listPlace>

        <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="DivineComedy">
                <title>The Divine Comedy</title>
                <author ref="#Dante">Dante Alighieri</author>
                <date when="1472">1472</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="WesternSeas">
                <title>Tales of the Western Seas</title>
                <author>N/A</author>
                <date>N/A</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="WorldHistory">
                <title>Peter Parley's World History</title>
                <author ref="#Parley">Peter Parley</author>
                <date>N/A</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="NationalReader">
                <title>The National Reader</title>
                <author ref="#Pierpont">John Pierpont</author>
                <date>1827</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="WilsonsReaders">
                <title>Wilson's Readers</title>
                <author>N/A</author>
                <date>N/A</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="OldTestament">
                <title>The Old Testament</title>
                <author>N/A</author>
                <date>N/A</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dora">
                <title>Dora</title>
                <author ref="#Tennyson">Alfred Tennyson</author>
                <date when="1886">1886</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Tanima">
                <title>Tanima no Himeyuri</title>
                <author ref="#Kencho">Suematso Kencho</author>
                <date when="1888" notBefore="1888" notAfter="1890">1888-1890</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="EnochArden">
                <title>Enoch Arden</title>
                <author ref="#Tennyson">Alfred Tennyson</author>
                <date when="1864">1864</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Hakkenden">
                <title>Nanso Satomi Hakkenden</title>
                <author ref="#Bakin">Kyokutei Bakin</author>
                <date when="1814" notBefore="1814" notAfter="1842">1814-1842</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ParadiseLost">
                <title>Paradise Lost</title>
                <author ref="#Milton">John Milton</author>
                <date when="1667">1667</date>
                <note/>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>

        <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="Etsu">
                <persName>Etsu Inagaki Sugimoto</persName>
                <birth>1874</birth>
                <death>1950</death>
                <note/> 
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Parley">
                <persName>Samuel Grisworld Goodrich (pseud. Peter Parley)</persName>
                <birth when="1793">1793</birth>
                <death when="1860">1860</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Pierpont">
                <persName>John Pierpoint</persName>
                <birth when="1785">1785</birth>
                <death when="1866">1866</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Dante">
                <persName>Dante Alighieri</persName>
                <birth when="1265">1265</birth>
                <death when="1321">1321</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Tennyson">
                <persName>Alfred Tennyson</persName>
                <birth when="1809">1809</birth>
                <death when="1892">1892</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Kencho">
                <persName>Suematsu Kencho</persName>
                <birth when="1855">1855</birth>
                <death when="1920">1920</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Bakin">
                <persName>Kyokutei Bakin</persName>
                <birth when="1767">1767</birth>
                <death when="1848">1848</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Milton">
                <persName>John Milton</persName>
                <birth when="1608">1608</birth>
                <death when="1674">1674</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Colombus">
                <persName>Christopher Colombus</persName>
                <birth when="1451">1451</birth>
                <death when="1506">1506</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Shoken">
                <persName>Empress Shoken</persName>
                <birth>1849</birth>
                <death>1914</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Cleopatra">
                <persName>Cleopatra</persName>
                <birth when="0069">69 BC</birth>
                <death when="0030">30 BC</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ChineseEmpress">
                <persName>Empress of Emperor Genso of Great China</persName>
                <birth/>
                <death/>
                <note/>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Confucius">
                <persName>Confucius</persName>
                <birth when="0551">551 BC</birth>
                <death when="0479">479 BC</death>
                <note/>
            </person>
        </listPerson>
    </standOff>
</TEI>
