<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>


<TEI xml:id="basicTEI.478-878" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">A Daughter of the Samurai</title>
                <author>Etsuko Sugimoto</author>
                <principal>Abigail Jackowski</principal>

                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcibing and Emcoding the text</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="amj">Abigail Jackowski</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>


            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>

                <publisher>Doubleday, Page &amp; Company for Japan Society</publisher>

                <date>2021</date>

            </publicationStmt>


            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"/>
            </notesStmt>




            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>

                    <title level="a">A Daughter of the Samurai</title>
                    <editor/>
                    <author>Etsu Inagaki Sugimoto</author>
                    <date>1925</date>
                    <publisher>Doubleday, Page &amp; Company for Japan Society</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <orgName> </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>


        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="20210302">
                <name>Abby Jackowski</name>
            </change>

            <change when="20210302"> <name>Abigail Jackowski</name> encoding A Daughter of the
                Samurai</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="98"/>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="ch11">
                <head type="number">CHAPTER XI</head>
                <head type="title">MY FIRST JOURNEY</head>
                <p>That was one of the long <placeName ref="#Nagaoka"> Nagaoka </placeName>winters.
                    For five months we saw only snow. In the early spring our relatives in Tokyo had
                    written that arrangements had been made for my school. From that time I had been
                    waiting impatiently for the mountain roads to become safe from avalanches; for
                    just as soon as we could travel <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName>
                    was to take me to the capital. </p>

                <p>At last the dykes <term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="dyke" target="#dyke"/>were
                    dry&#8211;that was where the snow always melted first&#8211;and we had a
                    "gathering-green" picnic as a farewell to my companions in <placeName
                    ref="#Nagaoka"> Nagaoka </placeName> One sunny morning a group of us, with
                    purple scarfs on our , heads and <term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="kimono"
                    />kimonos tucked up over our bright skirts, dotted the dykes <term xml:lang="jp"
                    resp="#amj" ref="dyk"/>slopes, each carrying a small basket and a bamboo knife
                    and filling the air with laughter and merry calls as we hurried up and down the
                    banks, trying to see how many different kinds of green each could find. Often in
                    later years I recall that happy day as my last gay time at home as a girl. </p>

                <p>Finally the mail carriers reported that the overhanging snow-cliffs had all
                    fallen and the slopes were clear. Soon after came the day of our departure. With
                    a heart half of elation, half of regret, I bade good-bye to <persName
                    ref="#HonourableGrandmother "> Honourable Grandmother </persName> and <persName
                    ref="#Mother"> Mother </persName> and with misty eyes was carefully tucked into
                    my jinrikisha<term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha"
                    target="jinrikisha"/> by <persName ref="#Brother"> Ishi </persName>. Then,
                    between lines of bowing friends, our two jinrikishas <term xml:lang="jp"
                    resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha"/>and a baggageladen horse led by a coolie started
                    on the eight-days' journey to Tokyo. </p>

                <p>Most of the way we travelled in jinrikishas<term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj"
                    ref="jinrikisha" target="jinrikisha"/>, changing</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>them at certain towns, but occasionally we had to go on horseback. My saddle was
                    a high box-seat; so <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName> and the coolie
                    rigged up a double-basket held by bands across the horse's back. I sat in one
                    part, and baggage filled the other. As we went around the steep, curving road on
                    the mountain side, I could lean over and look far, far down to the fisher
                    villages on the coast. But it was more interesting, as we got farther along, to
                    look across the deep valley to the sloping hillsides with their terraces of
                    ricefields&#8211;odd-shaped patches fitted in like the silk pieces of a Buddhist
                    priest's robe. In every little village of thatch-roofed huts was a shrine set
                    high in the midst of a few trees, and, half-hidden in a hollow beside a stream,
                    was whirling the great narrow wheel of a rice-mill. The air was so clear that I
                    could plainly see the awkward lunge of a water-buffalo as he dragged a wooden
                    plough along the furrows of one of the rice-patches, and I could even
                    distinguish a scarlet Bower stuck between the folds of the towel knotted about
                    the head of the coolie behind. In those days no one ever wore a living Bower,
                    except to carry it to the dead; so I knew he was taking it home for the house
                    shrine. I wondered what kind of a home he had.</p>
                <p>I think it was our third day when I noticed that we were leaving the snow
                    country. No longer did the towns have their sidewalks roofed, and these thatches
                    bore no rows of avalanche stones. The houses looked bare and odd-like a married
                    woman's face with newly shaved eyebrows. But we were not entirely beyond the
                    sight of snow, for as we skirted <placeName ref="#MyokoMountain"> Myoko Mountain
                    </placeName> we saw a good many drifts and patches. The jinrikisha <term
                    xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha" target="jinrikisha"/> men said snow
                    lasted there until July .</p>
                <p><q>"From the top,"</q>said <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName>, <q>"you
                    can see <placeName ref="#Fujiyama"> Fujiyama </placeName></q>&#8211; "</p>
                <p>My heart thrilled, and I foolishly turned my head, feeling for a moment that I
                    was really near the sacred</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>mountain which my eyes had never expected to behold. And then, with a deeper,
                    warmer thrill, I heard the conclusion of his sentence:</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"&#8211;and then, if you turn and look in the opposite direction, you can see
                        the plains of <placeName ref="#Echigo"> Echigo </placeName>."</q>
                </p>
                <p><q>"We are very far away from home,"</q> I replied in a small voice.</p>
                <p><persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName> gave a quick look at my grave face;
                    then he laughed.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"Also, if you look just beyond, you can see the <placeName ref="#IsleofSado">
                        Isle of Sado </placeName> .<persName ref="#Matsuo"> If Matsuo
                        </persName>should not come up to expectations, here's some advice for
                        you."</q>
                </p>
                <p>And his merry voice broke into an old song:</p>

                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <q>
                        <emph rend="italics">"Nikuiotoko ni ltiutai shima wa Royagoshi ni Sada ga
                            shima."</emph>
                    </q>
                </p>
                <p>I was shocked that<persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName>should sing a
                    common servant's song, and doubly shocked that he should joke so lightly about
                    serious things; so my face was still grave as we rolled along in our
                    jinrikishas<term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha" target="jinrikisha"
                    />.</p>

                <p>The <placeName ref="#IsleofSado"> Isle of Sado </placeName> used to be a place of
                    exile for criminalsand was considered by common people as the end of the world.
                    This joking song, which is popular among peasant girls, is literally a threat to
                    present to a disliked suitor, not the pleated garment which is the usual gift of
                    the bride to a groom, but instead, a convict's garb: meaning, <q>"I pray the
                    gods will send the unwelcome one across the raging seas to the end of the
                    world."</q></p>
                <p>We spent our fifth night at <placeName ref="#Nagano"> Nagano </placeName> in the
                    temple of <placeName ref="#Zenkoji"> Zenkoji </placeName> where lived theroyal
                    nun bene.athwhose high-lifted razor I had walked, years before, in a procession
                    of gaily clad little girls, for a Buddhist ceremony of consecration.</p>
                <p>The next morning, soon after we started, <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother
                    </persName> halted and allowed my jinrikisha <term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj"
                    ref="jinrikisha" target="jinrikisha"/>to roll up to his side.</p>
                <pb/>
                <p><q>"<persName ref="#Etsuko">Etsu-bo</persName>,"</q>he asked,<q>"When did they
                    give up making priestess of you?"</q></p>
                <p><q>"Why&#8211;I don't know,"</q>I said, suprised.</p>
                <p>He gave a little scornful laugh and rode on to his place ahead leaving me silent
                    and thoughtful.</p>
                <p>I had spoken the truth when I said I did not know. I had always accepted my
                    education with no thought of results. But <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother's
                    </persName> laugh had startled me, and, rolling along that mountain road, I did
                    a good deal of thinking. At last I believed that I understood. I know my father
                    had never approved, although he acquiesced in <persName
                    ref="#HonourableGrandmother "> Honourable Grandmother;s </persName> wish that I
                    should be educated for a priestess; and when, after my <persName ref="#Brother">
                    Brother's </persName> sad departure, he had quietly substituted
                    studieswhichwould be of benefit should I ever hold the position of his heir, I
                    think <persName ref="#HonourableGrandmother "> Honourable Grandmother
                    </persName>, aching with sympathy for her proud, disappointed son, laid aside
                    her cherished hope, and the plan was silently abandoned.</p>
                <p>In the province of <placeName ref="#Shinano"> Shinano </placeName>, an hour or so
                    from <placeName ref="#Nagano"> Nagano </placeName>, my jinrikisha <term
                    xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha" target="jinrikisha"/>man pointed
                    across the river to a small wooded mountain.</p>
                <p><q>"Obatsuyama, it is," </q>he said.</p>
                <p>How my mind went back to <persName ref="#Ishi"> Ishi </persName>and her
                    mother-love story which tells of a time long, long ago, when there lived at the
                    foot of this mountain a poor farmer and his aged widowed mother. They owned a
                    bit of land which supplied them with food and their humble lives were peaceful
                    and happy.</p>
                <p>At that time <placeName ref="#Shinano"> Shinano </placeName>was governed by a
                    despotic ruler who, though a brave warrior, had a great and cowardly shrinking
                    from anything suggestive of fading health and strength. This caused him to send
                    out a cruel proclamat:ion. The entire province was given strict orders
                    immediately to put to death all aged people.</p>
                <p>Those were barbarous days, and the custom of abandon-</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>ing old people to die was not uncommon. However, it was not a law, and many of
                    the helpless old lived as long as nature allowed in comfortable and welcome
                    homes. The poor farmer loved his aged mother with tender reverence, and the
                    order filled his heart with sorrow. But no one ever thought a second time about
                    obeying the mandate of a daimio, so with many deep and hopeless sighs the youth
                    prepared for what at that time was considered the kindest mode of death.</p>
                <p>Just at sundown, when hois day's work was ended, he took a quantity of the
                    unwhitened rice which is the principal food of the poor, cooked and dried it,
                    and tying it in a square of cloth he swung the bundle around his neck along with
                    a gourd filled with cool, sweet water. Then he lifted his helpless old mother to
                    his back and started on his painful journey up the mountain.</p>
                <p>The road was long and steep. He plodded- steadily on, the shadows growing deeper
                    and deeper, until the moon, round and clear, rose above the mountain-top and
                    peered pityingly through the branches upon the youth toiling onward, his head
                    bent with weariness and his heart heavy with sorrow. The narrow road was crossed
                    and recrossed by many paths made by hunters and wood-cutters. In some places
                    they mingled in a confused puzzle, but he gave no heed. One path or another, it
                    mattered not. On he went, climbing blindly upward&#8211;ever upward&#8211;toward
                    the high, bare summit of what is now known as <term xml:id="Oba" rend="sc"
                    >Obatsuyama</term>, mountain of the <q>"<gloss target="#Oba">Abandoning of the
                    Aged.</gloss>"</q></p>
                <p>The eyes of the old mother were not so dim out that they noted the reckless
                    hastening from one path to another, and her loving heart grew anxious. Her son
                    did not know the mountain's many paths, and his return might be one of danger,so
                    she stretched forth herhand and snapping the twigs from the bushes as they
                    passed, she</p>

                <pb/>
                <p>quietly dropped a handful every few steps of the way, so as they climbed, the
                    narrow path behind them was dotted at frequent intervals with tiny piles of
                    twigs.</p>
                <p>At last the summit was reached. Weary and heartsick, the youth gently released
                    his burden and silently prepared a place of comfort, as his last duty to the
                    loved one. Gathering fallen pine needles he made a soft cushion, and tenderly
                    lifting his old mother thereon, he wrapped her padded coat more closely about
                    the stooping shoulders and with tearful eyes and an aching heart said
                    farewell.</p>
                <p>The trembling mother voice was full of unselfish love as she gave her last
                    injunction.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"Let not thine eyes be blind, my son. The mountain road is full of danger.
                        Look carefully and follow the path which holds the piles of twigs. They will
                        guide thee to the familiar way farther down."</q>
                </p>
                <p>The son's surprised eyes looked back over the path, then at the 'poor old
                    shrivelled hands all scratched and soiled by their work of love. His heart smote
                    him and, bowing to the ground, he cried aloud:</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"Oh, Honourable Mother, thy kindness thrusts my heart! I will not leave thee.
                        Together'we will follow the path of twigs, and together we will die I"</q>
                </p>
                <p>Once more he shouldered his burden (how light it seemed now!) and hastened down
                    the path, through the shadows and the moonlight, to the little hut in the
                    valley.</p>
                <p>Beneath the kitchen floor was a walled closet for food, which was covered over
                    and hiddeμ from view. There the son hid his mother, supplying her with
                    everything needful and continually watching and fearing.</p>
                <p>Time passed and he was beginning to feel safe, when again the despot sent forth
                    heralds bearing an unreasonable and useless order; seemingly as a boast of his
                    power. His demand was that his subjects should present him with a rope of ashes.
                    The entire province trembled with</p>
                <pb/>

                <p>dread. The order must be obeyed; yet who in all <placeName ref="#Shinano">
                    Shinano </placeName>could make a rope of ashes?</p>
                <p>One night, in great distress, tne son whispered the news to his hidden
                    mother.</p>
                <p><q>"Wait!" </q> she said, <q>"I will think."</q></p>
                <p>On the second day she told him what to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"Make a rope of twisted straw," she said, "then stretch it upon a row of flat
                        stones and bum it there on a windless night."</q>
                </p>
                <p>He called the people together and did as she said, and when the blaze had died,
                    behold, upon the stones, with every twist and fibre showing perfect, lay a rope
                    of whitened ashes.</p>
                <p>The <persName ref="daimio">daimio </persName>was pleased at the wit of the youth,
                    and praised him greatly, but demanded to know where he had obtained his
                    wisdom.</p>
                <p><q>"Alas I Alas I"</q> cried the farmer, <q>"the truth must be told!"</q> and
                    with many deep bows he related his story.</p>
                <p>The daimio listened, then meditated in silence. Finally he lifted his head</p>
                <p><q>"<placeName ref="#Shinano"> Shinano </placeName>needs more than the strength
                    of youth,"</q> hesaid gravely.<q> "Ah, that I should have forgotten the
                    wellknown saying, 'With the crowri of snow, there cometh wisdom!'"</q></p>
                <p>That very hour the cruel law was abolished, and the custom drifted into so far a
                    past that only the legend remains.</p>
                <p>As we went farther on, I found the customs so different from those of <placeName
                    ref="#Nagaoka"> Nagaoka </placeName> that I felt as if I were already in a
                    strange land. At one place, long before we reached the village, we heard a
                    hoarse voice calling, <term xml:id="Ma" rend="sc"> Ma-kat-ta? Ma-kat-ta ?
                    </term>" <gloss target="#Ma">(Is it sold? Is it sold?)</gloss> and as we rolled
                    through the one narrow, crowded street we saw an auctioneer standing high in the
                    midst of dozens of bamboo baskets of beans, carrots, greens, and bamboo shoots;
                    while lying around him, in ungainly confusion, were every</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>size and shape of purple eggplant and long, sprawling, delicious lotus roots.</p>
                <p><persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName> looked back and laughed.</p>
                <p><q>"Who is he? What were all the people doing?"</q> I asked, as soon as we
                    reached the end of the long street and rolled out on to the public road.</p>
                <p><q>"It is a vegetable auction,"</q> <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName>
                    explained. <q>"Merchants buy in quantities, and every morning the things are
                    auctioned off by the basketful. Weren't those fine lotus roots? If we hadn't had
                    breakfast only a couple of hours ago I'd believe I was hungry."</q></p>
                <p>At another place we went by a house where death had entered. Before the door
                    stood a funeral palanquin into which coolies with big hats and crest-coats were
                    just lifting the heavy wooden bucket containing the body. Over it was thrown a
                    small kimono <term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jkimono" target="kimono"/>of
                    scarlet and gold, showing that the dead child must have been a little daughter.
                    The dress would have been white for a son. Around stood a number of white-robed
                    mourners with white towels folded over their hair. As we passed, I caught a
                    glimpse of a screen placed upside down and the lighted candles of a tiny
                    shrine.</p>
                <p>At one place, where the road ran close to a broad river with bold bluffs coming
                    down, in some places, almost to the water, we saw a number of odd floating
                    rice-mills with turning paddle-wheels that looked like a fleet of boats standing
                    motionless in a hopeless struggle against a strong tide. I wondered where, in
                    that rocky country, were enough people to eat all the rice that was being
                    r.round; but when we turned away from the river we suddenly found ourselves in a
                    silk-culture district, where our road ran through village after village, each
                    having its own mulberry plantation.</p>
                <p>The town where we expected to spend the night was only a few hours ahead when the
                    sky began to darken with a</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>threatening storm. <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName>was casting
                    anxious looks backward when his jinrikisha <term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj"
                    ref="jinrikisha" target="jinrikisha"/>man told him that in the next village was
                    a large house where travellers had sometimes been kept for a night. So we
                    hurried there, the last quarter of an hour being a bouncing, breathless race
                    between men and clouds. The men won, whirling us up to the door, into which we
                    ran unannounced, just as the storm broke with a downpour which it would have
                    been hard to struggle through on the road.</p>
                <p>It was an odd house where we had found shelter; but I know that even my
                    honourable father, on his journeys in ancient days, never, on any occasion,
                    received a more cordial welcome or more kindly treatment than did we and our
                    perspiring, laughing, boasting men at the end of our exciting race.</p>
            </div>

            <pb n="107"/>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="ch12">
                <head type="number">CHAPTER XI</head>
                <head type="title">TRAVEL EDUCATION</head>
                <p>The large, well-cared-for house in which we had taken refuge that stormy night
                    was crowded full of busy workers. With the exception of the living l'ooms of our
                    host, his wife, and two daughters, the entire house was full of skeleton frames
                    containing tiers and tiers of bamboo trays, each holding a network screen
                    covered with silkworms. There must have been thousands and thousands of them. I
                    had been accustomed to silkworms all my life. <persName ref="#Ishi"> Ishi's
                    </persName>home had been in a weaving village, and my elder sister had many silk
                    villages on her three-mountain estate; but I never before had spent a night in
                    sound of the continual nibbling of the hungry little creatures. It filled the
                    whole house with a gentle rustling, exactly like the patter of raindrops on dry
                    leaves, and I dreamed all night of dripping eaves. The next morning I awakened
                    with a depressed feeling that I was to have a day's ride in a close-shut
                    jinrikisha<term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha" target="jinrikisha"
                    />, and was surprised, when I pushed back one of the wooden panels at the porch
                    edge, to find that the sun was shining.</p>
                <p>While I was standing there, one of the daughters, about my age, came out carrying
                    a straw mat of silkworm waste to throw on a pile in the yard-for the mulberry
                    stems and rice hulls of silkworm waste make the best fertilizer in the world-and
                    she stopped to bow good-morning. Then she stood there in the June sunshine with
                    her sleeves looped back and her bare feet in straw sandals, and I squatted</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>on the edge of the porch in my home-dyed night kimono <term xml:lang="jp"
                    resp="#amj" ref="kimono" target="kimono"/>, and we got acquainted.</p>
                <p>She told me that she took care of six trays of silkworms all by herself. She
                    seemed to know everything about them, and she loved them.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"They're clean," she said, "and dainty about food, and intelligent about
                        their own affairs&#8211;just like people."</q>
                </p>
                <p>I was so interested in all the surprising things I heard that I was still
                    listening when a girl came to fold away my bed cushions, and I had to hurry to
                    get dressed.</p>
                <p> <q>"Well,"</q> said <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName>, after my room
                    had been cleaned, and breakfast brought in, <q> "how do you like living in a
                    boarding house?"</q> </p>
                <p><q>"The boarders are very noisy,"</q> I replied; <q>"and, from what our hostess's
                    daughter told me, they are very particular. She says they cannot endure one
                    particle of dust. Even a withered leaf will sometimes cause one to 'tie on his
                    blue neckerchief' and creep to the outer edge of the tray."</q></p>
                <p><q>"Have you seen our host's grandmother?"</q> asked <persName ref="#Brother">
                    Brother </persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"No, I didn't know there was a grandmother."</q>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <q>"She went early to her cushions last night; probably to escape the bustle and
                        annoyance of our abrupt arrival. We will pay our respects to her before we
                        leave."</q>
                </p>
                <p>When breakfast was over, our host took us to the grandmother's room. She was a
                    very old lady with a reserved manner and a face of more than usual intelligence.
                    As soon as she bowed I knew that she had been trained in a samurai house, and
                    when I saw the crest of a <emph rend="italics">naginata</emph> on the wall-rest
                    above the <emph rend="italics">shoji</emph>, I knew why <persName ref="#Brother"
                    > Brother </persName> had wanted me to come to this room. </p>
                <p> A <emph rend="italics">naginata</emph> is a long, light spear with curved blade,
                    which samurai women were taught to use, partly for exercise and partly for
                    defence in case of necessity. This </p>
                <pb/>
                <p>one bore the crest of one of our northern heroes. He was a traitor, but
                    nevertheless he was a hero. When he was killed, his daughter was one of the
                    group&#8211;three of them womenAs I mounted my jinrikisha <term xml:lang="jp"
                    resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha" target="jinrikisha"/> and bowed again to the entire
                    group of family and servants bowing in the doorway, I could not help sending a
                    thought farewell to the busy little boarders. I had learned more about silkworms
                    during that shon rustling visit than in my fourteen years of life in a silkworm
                    district. As we rolled along over a smooth, monotonous road my mind was busy,
                    and I believe that then and there I first began to realize vaguely-that all
                    creatures, however insignificant, were "intelligent about their own affairs-just
                    like people."who defended the sorely pressed castle during the last desperate
                    hours of hopeless struggle. The old lady told us, with modest pride, that she
                    had been a humble attendant of the daughter and was with her at that dreadful
                    time. The <emph rend="italics">naginata</emph> was a memory gift from her
                    honourable and beloved mistress.</p>
                <p>Seeing that we were deeply interested, she brought out her other treasure--a
                    slender, blunt knife called a <emph rend="italics">kogai</emph>, which, with the
                    throwing-dagger, forms part of the hilt of a samurai's long sword. In very
                    ancient days Japanese warfare was a science. Artistic skill was always displayed
                    in the use of weapons, and no soldier was proud of having wounded an enemy in
                    any other manner than the one established by strict samurai rule. The long sword
                    had for its goal only four points: the top of the head, the wrist, the side, and
                    the leg below the knee. The throwingdagger must speed on its way, true as an
                    arrow, direct to forehead, throat, or wrist. But the blunt little <emph
                    rend="italics"> kogai </emph>had many uses. It was the key that locked the sword
                    in its scabbard; when double it could be used as chopsticks by the marching
                    soldier; it has been used on the battlefield, or in retreat, mercifully to
                    pierce the ankle vein of a suffering and dying comrade, and it had the unique
                    use in a clan feud, when found sticking upright in the ankle of a dead foe, of
                    bearing the silent challenge, "I await thy return." Its crest told to whom it
                    belonged and, in time, it generally was returned-to its owner's ankle. The <emph
                    rend="italics"> kogai </emph>figures in many tales of romance and revenge of the
                    Middle Ages.</p>
                <p>I was glad to see <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName> so interested,
                    and was happy myself in watching the old lady's face flush and light up with her
                    memories; but her closing words made me feel</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>sorry. To some remark of <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother's </persName> she
                    replied,<q> "Youth is always listening eagerly for marching orders; but the aged
                    can only look backward to sad memories and hopeless dreams."</q></p>
                <p>As I mounted my jinrikisha <term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha"
                    target="#jinrikisha"/>and bowed again to the entire group of family and servants
                    bowing in the doorway, I could not help sending a thought farewell to the busy
                    little boarders. I had learned more about silkworms during that shon rustling
                    visit than in my fourteen years of life in a silkworm district. As we rolled
                    along over a smooth, monotonous road my mind was busy, and I believe that then
                    and there I first began to realize&#8211; vaguely&#8211;that all creatures,
                    however insignificant, were "intelligent about their own affairs&#8211;just like
                    people."</p>
                <p><q>"Dear me I"</q> I finally said to myself. <q>"How much we learn when we travel
                    I"</q> and I pulled the jinrikisha <term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj"
                    ref="jinrikisha"/>robe over my lap and settled myself for the long ride
                    ahead.</p>
                <p>I think I must have gone to sleep, for I found myself crookedly but comfortably
                    snuggled into almost a <emph rend="italics">kinoji </emph>when I heard <persName
                    ref="#Brother"> Brother's </persName> voice.</p>
                <p>We were entering a good-sized town and he was leaning back and pointing across
                    the tiled roofs to a castle on the hill beyond.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"This is <placeName ref="#Komoro"> Komoro </placeName>," he called, "and
                        there's where the foot-high dolls came from."</q>
                </p>
                <p>I smiled as my mind flew back to the <placeName ref="#Nagaoka"> Nagaoka
                    </placeName> home and pictured two enormous dolls of the festival set brought by
                    our <placeName ref="#Komoro"> Komoro </placeName> great-great-grandmother with
                    her wedding dowry. In her day the Government permitted only the daughter of a
                    daimio to own dolls a foot high, and her entire set must have been wondrously
                    handsome. But in my time, when our living came principally from ,he visits of
                    the second-hand man to our godown, the wondnful <placeName ref="#Komoro"> Komoro
                    </placeName>dolls, with their miniature furniture of gc Id and lacquer&#8211;the
                    perfection of Japanese art of the Middle</p>

                <pb/>
                <p>Ages&#8211;gradually found new homes. They went, I know, to no godown of Japan,
                    but, through some shrewd dealer, into foreign hands and foreign lands and
                    probably to-day are calmly resting in widely scattered homes and museums of
                    Europe or America.</p>
                <p>Two of the dolls had become defaced in some way, and thus, being unsaleable, they
                    were placed as ornaments on the high tokonoma<term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj"
                    ref="tokonoma" target="#tokonoma"/> shelf in my room. I was very fond of acting
                    out scenes of the stories that were told me, and I used to take down the dolls
                    and use them as an audience while I strutted around the room representing an
                    ancient samurai with some fearful duty to perform. The dolls' heads were
                    movable, and thus supplied a splendid opportunity for a favourite revenge story
                    of mine. Many a time I have placed my hand on one of the enamelled heads and,
                    with my ivory paper knife as a sword, have struck fiercely at the doll, at the
                    same instant lifting out the head from its collar of rich brocade; then, with
                    stern, set face, I would hurriedly wrap the head in a purple square of crepe
                    and, tucking it under my arm, stride boldly off to an imaginary courtroom.</p>
                <p>I suspect my father knew of this barbarous game of mine, for I always borrowed
                    his purple crepe <emph rend="italics"> fukusa </emph>for this purpose, feeling
                    that something belonging to him would give dignity to the occasion; but I never
                    heard <persName ref="#HonourableGrandmother "> Honourable Grandmother's
                    </persName> step on the porch that I did not quickly restore the head to its
                    brocade nest in order to save her another anxious fear that I was growing too
                    bold and rough ever to find a husband.</p>
                <p>As our jinrikishas <term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha"
                    target="#jinrikisha"/>rolled through the town I looked up at the castle with
                    interest. And this was the home from which our <placeName ref="#Komoro"> Komoro
                    </placeName> grandmother had gone forth on her wedding journey to <placeName
                    ref="#Nagaoka"> Nagaoka </placeName> ! Half buried in trees it stood, the gray,
                    tipped-up corners of many roofs peeping through the branches. It looked like a
                    broad, low pa-</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>goda towering above a slanting wall of six-sided stones the "tortoise back" of
                    all Japanese castles.</p>
                <p>From <placeName ref="#Komoro"> Komoro </placeName> to <placeName ref="#Nagaoka">
                    Nagaoka </placeName> It must have seemed a long trip to the young girl in the
                    teetering bridal <emph rend="italics">kago !</emph> I thought of what <persName
                    ref="#HonourableGrandmother "> Honourable Grandmother </persName> had told me of
                    her own month-long bridal trip. And then I looked ahead. The ldzumo <term
                    xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="Idzumo" target="Idzumo"/> gods, who plan all
                    marriages, had decreed the same fate for many brides of our family, and, so far
                    as my own future was planned, I seemed destined to follow in the footsteps of my
                    ancestors.</p>
                <p>At one place where we had to take <emph rend="italics"> kagos</emph> I disgraced
                    myself. I dreaded a <emph rend="italics"> kago</emph>. The big basket swinging
                    from the shoulders of the trotting coolies always made me dizzy and faint, but
                    that day it was raining hard and the mountain path was too rough for a
                    jinrikisha<term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha" target="jinrikisha"
                    />. I stood things as bravely as I could, but finally I became so sick that
                    <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName> had the baggage taken off the
                    horse and, wedging me in between cushions on its back, covered me with a tent
                    made of a straw mat and, disdaining comfort for himself, walked all the way up
                    the mountain beside me, the coolie following with the two <emph rend="italics">
                    kagos</emph>.</p>
                <p>At the top the sun was shining, and when I peeped out from my tent <persName
                    ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName>was shaking himself as my poor Shiro <term
                    xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="shiro" target="shiro"/>used to do when drenched
                    with rain. I ventured to apologize in a shamed voice.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"<emph rend="italics">Kago</emph>sickness is a great absorber of pride,
                        <persName ref="#Etsuko">Etsu-bo</persName>. I'm afraid you have lost your
                        right to be called your father's 'brave son."'</q>
                </p>
                <p>I laughed, but my cheeks were hot.</p>
                <p>As he helped me to the ground, <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName>
                    pomted toward a wide-spreading cloud of smoke floating lazily above a
                    cone-shaped mountain.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"That's the signpost for the Robber Station," he said. "Do you remember?"</q>
                </p>
                <p>Indeed I did. Many times I had heard Father tell the</p>

                <pb/>
                <p>story of the small hotel at the top of a mountain where the rates were so high
                    that people called it the 'Robber Station.' I was a big girl before I learned
                    that it was a very respectable stopping place and not a den of thieves where
                    money was extorted from travellers as tribute.</p>
                <p>We walked down the mountain, passing several cave shrines. In one I caught the
                    twinkle of a burning lamp. lt reminded me of the hermit caves of <placeName
                    ref="Echigo">Echigo</placeName>. This was rr.y first long trip from home, and it
                    was full of strange new experiences. Yet there seemed to be familiar memories
                    connected with everything. I wondered vaguely if I should find it so in
                    America.</p>
                <p>One day, after a shower, as the man stopped to lower the top of my
                    jinrikisha<term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha" target="#jinrikisha"
                    />, a sudden burst of sunshine showed rre, high up on the mountain-side, pressed
                    flat against the green, an immense white <term xml:id="dai" rend="sc"
                    >dai</term>, <gloss target="#dai">the Japanese character meanirg
                    "great.</gloss>" It looked as if it had been painted with a brush, but <persName
                    ref="#Jiya">Jiya</persName>, who had once been there, had told me that it was
                    made of strips of bamboo covered thickly with paper prayers tied on by pilgrim
                    visitors to the temple en top of the mountain.</p>
                <p>Near by was the rude little village where <persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo </persName>
                    lived. She was <persName ref="#Jiya">Jiya's</persName> sister, and we spent the
                    night in her house. It was a queer place, a sort of cheap hotel for country
                    people. <persName ref="Miyo">Miyo</persName>, with her son and his wife, met us
                    at the door with deep bows and many a <emph rend="italics">"Maa ! Maa !"
                    </emph>of surprise and pleasure. The wide entrance opened into a big room having
                    a clay floor. Several casks bound with hoops of twisted bamboo were piled in one
                    corner, and from the smoky ceiling hung a bulging bag of grain, bunches of mochi
                    <emph rend="italics">mochi</emph> cakes and dried fish, and bamboo baskets
                    containing provisions of various kinds. </p>
                <p>We passed through a mob of chattering pilgrims who had just come down from the
                    mountain, and, crossing the stones of a crude little garden, reached the
                    rooms</p>
                <pb/>

                <p>where <persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo </persName>lived. Everything was clean, but the
                    paper doors were patched, the mats yellow with age, and the cloth bindings worn
                    almost through. <persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo </persName>character who, in
                    violation of all tradition, had cast off a worthless husband and brought up her
                    four children herself. Of course it was very low class to do a thing like that,
                    but she was as brave as a man, and, since her husband had no parents, she had
                    been able legally to keep the children herself.</p>
                <p><persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo </persName>had been a servant in our house when
                    <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName> was a child, and her delight in
                    seeing the "Young Master" was pathetic. Her bare feet went pattering over the
                    mats, slipping quickly into her sandals each time she crossed the door-sill to
                    the kitchen. She hurried here and there, bringing us the best she had and
                    offering everything with bows and apologies. One thing troubled her very much.
                    She had only wooden trays with no feet, and she had never known my <persName
                    ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName> to eat off a low tray. In the days when she
                    lived at our house, even an informal serving of cake was presented to him on a
                    high lacquer stand, just as it was to Father. But she was ingenious, and
                    presently she brought in a brassbound rice-bucket and with many bows and an
                    anxious "Please grant your honourable pardon!" placed the tray on it before
                    <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName>. He laughed heartily and said
                    that even a shogun had never received a similar honour.</p>
                <p>We sat up very late and had a most interesting time. <persName ref="#Brother">
                    Brother </persName> talked of past days and of many things about our home, so
                    little known to me that I felt as if I were reading some old, half-familiar
                    book. I had never known him to be so free and merry as he was that evening. And
                    <persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo </persName>, half laughter and half tears, talked
                    rapidly, asking many questions and interrupting herself continually. She was</p>

                <pb/>
                <p>reminding him of some incident of his childhood, when he abruptly asked: <q>"What
                    became of your 'own-choice' husband, <persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo
                    </persName>?"</q></p>
                <p>I thought that question was too cruel, but <persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo
                    </persName> calmly replied: <q>"Young Master, 'The rust of one's own sword can
                    be brightened only by one's own effort.' I am still paying the penalty of my
                    life mistake."</q></p>
                <p>Very gravely she went across the room to a big chest and took out a small, flat
                    package. It was a square of purple crepe bearing our crest. With a serious face
                    she unfolded it, showing a brocade charm bag such as we children used to wear to
                    hold the paper blessing of the priest. The gold threads were a little ravelled
                    and the heavy scarlet cord mellowed with age.</p>
                <p><persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo </persName>lifted it reverently to her forehead.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"The Honourable Mistress gave it to me," she said to <persName ref="#Brother"
                        > Brother </persName>, "the night she let my lover and me through the water
                        gate. It held square silver coins&#8211;all that I needed."</q>
                </p>

                <p> <q>"Ah!"</q> <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother </persName>exclaimed excitedly,
                    <q>"I know! I was a little boy. It was dark and I saw her coming back alone,
                    carrying a lantern. But I never understood what it meant."</q></p>
                <p><persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo </persName>hesitated a moment; then she told us.</p>
                <p>When she was employed in our house, she was very young, and because she was the
                    sister of Father's faithful <persName ref="#Jiya">Jiya</persName>, she was
                    allowed much freedom. A youthful servant, also of our house, fell in love with
                    her. For young people to become lovers without the sanction of proper
                    formalities was a grave offence in any class, but in a samurai household it was
                    a black disgrace to the house. The penalty was exile through the water
                    gate&#8211;a gate of brush built over a stream and never used except by one of
                    the <term xml:id="eta" rend="sc">eta</term>, <gloss target="#eta"> or
                    outcast</gloss>,. The departure was public, and the culprits were</p>
                <pb/>

                <p>ever after shunned by everyone. The penalty was unspeakably cruel, but in the old
                    days severe measures were used as a preventive of law-breaking.</p>
                <p>Mother always rigidly obeyed every law of the household, but she saved
                    <persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo </persName> from public disgrace by taking the
                    lovers quietly, at midnight, and herself opening the big swinging gate for them
                    to pass. No one ever knew the truth.</p>
                <p><q>"It is said," </q>concluded <persName ref="#Miyo"> Miyo </persName>sadly,
                    <q>"that the hearts of those who pass the water gate are purified by the gods;
                    but even so, the penalty of a law-breaker can never be evaded. In secret I have
                    paid the penalty, and my children were saved from disgrace by the heavenly
                    kindness of the Honourable Mistress of the Inagaki."</q></p>
                <p>We all sat quiet for a moment. Then <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother
                    </persName>said bitterly:</p>
                <p>
                    <q>"The Honourable Mistress of the Inagaki was many times more merciful to the
                        servants of her household than to her one and only son."</q>
                </p>
                <p>Impatiently he pushed his cushion aside and abruptly said good-night.</p>
                <p>The next morning our road wound along the side of a mountain stream awkwardly
                    threading its way through a series of angular gullies, finally ending abruptly
                    in a swift, sloping leap into a wide, shallow river, which we crossed on a boat
                    poled by coolies. This river was the scene of one of <persName ref="#Jiya"
                    >Jiya's</persName> most exciting stories. Father, on one of his hurried trips to
                    Tokyo, had found it flooded and had ordered his coolies to place his palanquin
                    on a platform and carry it on their heads through the whirling waves to the
                    opposite shore. One man was drowned.</p>
                <p>As our jinrikishas<term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha"
                    target="#jinrikisha"/> rolled along I thought of how often Father had gone over
                    that road amidst the state and pomp of old Japan; and now his two dear
                    ones&#8211;his eldest and his youngest&#8211;were following the same path in
                    rented</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>jinrikishas<term xml:lang="jp" resp="#amj" ref="jinrikisha" target="#jinrikisha"
                    />, simply garbed and with no attendants except a wheezy old coolie with a
                    baggage horse. How strange it seemed.</p>
                <p>At last we reached <placeName ref="#Takasaki">Takasaki </placeName>&#8211;the
                    place from which the celebrated "land steamer" started on its puffing way to
                    Tokyo. That was the first time that I ever saw a railway train. It looked to me
                    like a long row of little rooms, each with a narrow door opening on to the
                    platform.</p>
                <p>It was late in the afternoon, and I was so weary that I have little recollection
                    of anything except a scolding from <persName ref="#Brother"> Brother
                    </persName>, because I, feeling that I was entering some kind of a house,
                    stepped out of my wooden shoes, leaving them on the platform. Just before the
                    train started, they were handed in at the window by an official whose special
                    duty it was to gather all the shoes from the platform before the starting of
                    every train. I went to sleep at once, and the next thing I knew we were in
                    Tokyo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>

    <standOff>
        <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="Brother">
                <persName> Brother</persName>
                <occupation>Business man</occupation>
                <note> Brother is a traditional Japanese boy and heads to the Army once he is old
                    enough. He was then seeing the success of people in America and intrigued on how
                    to get over there. Not too long later Brother was offered his first job of a
                    partnership in America and took the job. He was the first one in his family to
                    go to America inspriring the rest of his siblings to follow in his path. </note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Matsuo">
                <persName> Matsuo</persName>
                <occupation>Business man</occupation>
                <note>Matsuo came into Brother's life after Brother got in a terrible accident and
                    was sent to the hospital. Matsuo saw how bad he was doing and tried to help him
                    becoming his caretaker which started their friendship. Matsuo then becomes more
                    involved with the Etsu's family and they decide to set them up with a
                    marriage. </note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="HonourableGrandmother">
                <persName> Honorouble Grandmother</persName>
                <occupation>Caretaker</occupation>
                <note>Grandmother often spent her days relaxing around the house and reading to
                    Etsu when she was younger. Etsuko's grandmother has a big impact on her
                    education and pushes for Etsu to get better eductaion than what is provided
                    for girls at this time as she wants Etsuko to be a priestess. Grandmother alway
                    pushed Etsu to be maiden-like in order to follow Japenese tradition. </note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Ishi">
                <persName> Ishi</persName>
                <occupation>Nurse</occupation>
                <note> Ishi comes into Etsu's life as her nurse. She was often the one who took care
                    of Etsu, Brother, and Sister in the early years. Ishi is motherlike figure in
                    for Etsu as Ishi makes her clothes, food, and also dresses her everyday when
                    she was younger. Ishi also teaches Etsuko important skills for a woman in
                    japenesse culture such as sewing. </note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Miyo">
                <persName> Miyo</persName>
                <occupation>servant</occupation>
                <note>Miyo is the sister of Jiya and was a previous servant when Brother was a
                    child. She then left her role when she had children without being married. This
                    was a disgrace to traditions in Japan as people could get exiled for this
                    behavior. Miyo is used in the story to teach her children a lesson regarding
                    Japanese traditions.</note>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="Jiya">
                <persName> Jiya</persName>
                <occupation>Head Servavent</occupation>
                <note>Jiya is the head servant of Estu's father having command over the other
                    servants. Jiya is an extremely strict leader but is often described as a very
                    caring and loyal person in Etsu's eyes. He was typically always busy working but
                    always made time to help or hangout with Etsuko. Jiya becomes more involved with
                    the family as he begins to help out with the Father's business. Jiya begins to
                    start taking over when Father is busy and even accompanies him on business
                    trips.</note>
            </person>
        </listPerson>

        <listPlace>
            <place xml:id="Nagaoka" type="city">
                <placeName>Nagaoka</placeName>
                <location>
                    <country> Japan</country>
                    <settlement>Niigata</settlement>
                    <geo>37.4465, 138.8513</geo>
                </location>
                <desc>This city is where </desc>
            </place>

            <place xml:id="MyokoMountain" type="stratovolcano">
                <placeName>Myoko Mounatin</placeName>
                <location>
                    <country>Japan</country>
                    <settlement>Honshu</settlement>
                    <geo>36.8925, 138.1130</geo>
                </location>

            </place>
            <place xml:id="Fujiyama" type="mountain">
                <placeName>Fujiyama</placeName>
                <location>
                    <country>Japan</country>
                    <settlement>Honshu</settlement>
                    <geo>35.3606, 138.7274</geo>
                </location>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Echigo" type="province">
                <placeName>Echigo</placeName>
                <location>
                    <country>Japan</country>
                    <settlement>Honshu</settlement>
                    <geo>37.8154, 138.9077</geo>
                </location>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="IsleofSado" type="island">
                <placeName>Isle of Sado</placeName>
                <location>
                    <country>Japan</country>
                    <settlement>Niigata</settlement>
                    <geo>38.0411, 138.3387</geo>
                </location>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Nagano" type="city">
                <placeName>Nagano</placeName>
                <location>
                    <country>Japan</country>
                    <settlement>Nagano Prefecture</settlement>
                    <geo>36.6485, 138.1950</geo>
                </location>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Zenkoji" type="temple">
                <placeName>Zenkoji</placeName>
                <location>
                    <country>Japan</country>
                    <settlement>Nagano</settlement>
                    <geo>36.6617, 138.1877</geo>
                </location>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Shinano" type="Province">
                <placeName>Shinano</placeName>
                <location>
                    <country>Japan</country>
                    <settlement>Honshu</settlement>
                    <geo>36.8064, 138.2072</geo>
                </location>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Komoro" type="city">
                <placeName>Komoro</placeName>
                <location>
                    <country>Japan</country>
                    <settlement>Nagano Prefecture</settlement>
                    <geo>36.3271, 138.4258</geo>
                </location>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Takasaki" type="city">
                <placeName>Takasaki</placeName>
                <location>
                    <country>Japan</country>
                    <settlement>Gumna</settlement>
                    <geo>36.3221, 139.0034</geo>
                </location>
            </place>
        </listPlace>

        <listAnnotation>
<note><hi rend="bold">Foreign Words:</hi></note>
            <annotation xml:id="dyke" motivation="describing" target="#dyke">
                <note>Dyke: typically describes the flow of water that is stopped by a barrier to
                    the water out of the sea. This can also be used to keep rivers from
                    flooding.</note>
            </annotation>
            <annotation xml:id="jinrikisha" motivation="describing" target="#jinrikisha">
                <note>Jinrikisha: a Japenese word describing a small cart used to carry passengers.
                    The cart is then pulled by a one person and it used often for transportation in
                    Japan.</note>
            </annotation>
            <annotation xml:id="kimono" motivation="describing" target="#kimono">
                <note>Kimono: a Japenese word for "thing to wear" and is a traditional clothing item
                    worn in Japan made out of a cloth known as a tanmono. It is a dress like outift
                    that is then held together by a belt known as an obi. This is not typically worn
                    everyday but specifically for special occassions and events. </note>
            </annotation>
            <annotation xml:id="shiro" motivation="describing" target="#shiro">
                <note>Shiro: a Japenese word meaning white or castle. In this text this word is
                    being used to describe Estsuko father's dog. </note>
            </annotation>
            <annotation xml:id="tokonoma" motivation="describing" target="#tokonoma">
                <note>Tokonoma: a Japenese word describing a space in a room used to display
                    artistic items.</note>
            </annotation>
        </listAnnotation>
    </standOff>
</TEI>
